Nikita Kozodoi, Ph.D.

ML researcher working on the frontier of research and business. With Ph.D. in ML and certified AWS ML knowledge, practical experience in different ML/DL areas and strong communication skills, I am passionate about using AI to solve challenging business problems. My recent projects focus on ML for credit risk analytics and DL for computer vision.

♦ kozodoi.me (portfolio & ML blog)

in linkedin.com/in/kozodoi

github.com/kozodoi

☑ n.kozodoi@icloud.com

Experience

04/2018 - 03/2022 Data Science Research Associate, Monedo / Humboldt University, Berlin.

- developed sample bias mitigation algorithms to improve model profitability by up to 3%
- o reduced data acquisition costs by up to 25% using multi-objective feature selection methods
- o benchmarked fair ML algorithms to identify methods enhancing fairness at the smallest cost
- o published 5 ML papers with over 80 total citations and delivered 5 conference talks [Papers]

09/2018 - 08/2020 Project-Based Data Scientist, Simply Rational, Berlin, freelance.

- o identified customer segments and prototyped segment prediction models from incomplete data
- o determined suitable treatments from A/B tests results and presented findings to corporate clients

07/2016 - 03/2018 Research Assistant, Max Planck Institute for Human Development, Berlin.

- o benchmarked ML algorithms against simple heuristics and analyzed key performance drivers
- Education
- 04/2018 03/2022 Ph.D. in Machine Learning, Information Systems, Humboldt University, Berlin.

Research on ML/DL for credit scoring. Teaching ML. Supervising student theses. Grade: summa cum laude.

10/2015 - 12/2017 M.Sc. in Economics, Quantitative Methods, Humboldt University, Berlin, GPA: 1.30 (A).

Focused on Data Science and Predictive Analytics. Thesis topic: ML for box office forecasting.

09/2010 - 06/2014**B.Sc. in Economics**, *Higher School of Economics*, Moscow, GPA: 1.31 (A).

Focused on Statistics and Econometrics. Top-1 in the 4-year student ranking. Diploma with Honors.

Certifications

- 01/2022 AWS Certified Machine Learning, AWS. Learned training, tuning and deploying ML models on AWS.
- 06/2020 Deep Learning Nanodegree, Udacity. Implemented CNNs, RNNs and LSTMs in PyTorch.
- 05/2020 Machine Learning Engineer Nanodegree, Udacity. Deployed ML models on Amazon SageMaker.

Further certificates and course descriptions are available on my website. [Certificates]

Selected ML Projects

05/2021 – 08/2021 **Text Readability Prediction.** Developed a PyTorch pipeline for text complexity prediction with transformers.

Deployed a web app for scoring custom texts. Placed top-9% in the Kaggle competition. [App] [GitHub]

03/2021 - 06/2021 Image-to-Text Molecular Translation. Translated molecule images into chemical formulas with PyTorch. Built a CNN-LSTM architecture for image captioning. Placed top-5% in the Kaggle competition. [GitHub]

09/2019 - 04/2021 Fairness: Package for Fair ML. Building and maintaining an R package with over 17k total downloads. Implemented calculation and visualization of fairness metrics. Wrote documentation. [Blog post] [GitHub]

09/2018 - present Kaggle Master. Won 18 competition medals. Top-1% of the global user ranking. [Projects]

Selected ML Publications

06/2020 - present ML Blog. Publishing ML/DL tutorials and project overviews. Reached over 10k monthly page views. [Blog]

- 11/2021 Fairness in credit scoring: Assessment, implementation and profit implications, EJOR. [Paper] [GitHub]
- 04/2020 Shallow self-learning for reject inference in credit scoring, ECML PKDD. [Paper] [Meetup talk]
- 05/2019 A multi-objective approach for profit-driven feature selection in credit scoring, DSS. [Paper]

Technical Stack

Tools 🥠 Python, R, SQL (interm) 🖵 VSCode, Jupyter 🌰 AWS Cloud (SageMaker, EC2) 👫 GitHub, Trello Packages E Pandas, NumPy SpyTorch, TensorFlow (interm) 👬 Scikit-learn, XGBoost 🖾 Timm, Huggingface

Soft Skills

Languages English (C2), German (C1), Russian (native)

o strong motivation to learn and improve o attention to detail and scientific mindset

- o excellent communication skills [Public talks]
- o rich experience of working in team projects